You ask a question to ChatGPT and
it will give you the answer in 2
seconds.
But, after those 2 seconds,
the OpenAI company has to spend 100
million dollars to build ChatGPT.
Yes, let me repeat, the OpenAI
company has spent 900 crores to
build ChatGPT.
Now, my question is,
how is it able to understand our
questions and answer each and every
one of your questions in every
single domain?
And that is exactly what we are
going to learn in this video.
How do you build large language
models like ChatGPT, Claude,
Gemini?
We will understand every single
thing step by step with very simple
examples.
Now, let's understand how an LLM is
being trained.
So, we will understand this with an
example.
The example is, raising a child.
There are actually 4 stages to this
LLM training.
So, the first stage is,
assume that our child goes to a
school.
And after going to that school,
he will try to absorb a lot of data.
May be data from the books,
may be data from the conversations,
may be data from the world.
And he is trying to absorb every
single thing.
The point here is, that child is
consuming the data, but not
understanding it completely.
He is just understanding the
patterns.
For example, let's say,
after saying good morning or thank,
he will continue to say you.
Here, the main point is,
he is absorbing the data.
So, in summary, the child doesn't
know the meanings yet.
They just know the patterns.
Now, let's go to the stage 2.
In stage 2, a teacher comes into the
picture.
What does the teacher tell the
child?
If someone asks a question,
how to answer?
That is what the teacher will do.
What is important here is,
the teacher is not giving the
knowledge,
but the teacher is giving the
manners, structure and format to the
responses.
And now, the stage 3.
In stage 3, the child will go into
the real world.
He will interact with the humans.
Sometimes, the child will make the
mistakes, he will make right
answers,
he will make bad answers,
he will give you some violating
answers.
So, what do these people do?
They will provide feedback.
They will tell you what to do,
what not to do.
Now, based on all of this feedback,
he is going to learn
and he is going to update his
answers.
So, in summary, the child is going
to learn from the human feedback
what to say and what not to say,
to being polite.
And then, the 4th stage.
In many videos, they will skip this
stage
and this is what we call as an
inference.
Now, what happened?
The child learned in the school
and then the teacher told him how to
talk
and after he came out,
people gave him feedback.
He learned even better.
Now, he is ready.
Now, you go and ask the child some
question.
He will answer you politely.
Yes or no?
Now, based on this context,
we will understand what exactly is
an LLM.
Now, our child is there,
right?
The brain in the child is there,
That is what we call it as an LLM.
Which is called Large Language and
Model.
Now, our companies like ChatGPT,
Claude, Gemini,
all of these companies,
they have built these models.
They have built these brains.
Those are what we call it as an LLM.
Now, let's go back to our first
information.
So, we have 4 stages, right?
For these 4 stages,
they have some technical names.
Stage 1 is what we call it as a pre
-training.
And stage 2 is what we call it as a
supervised fine -tuning.
And the third stage is
RLHF, reinforcement learning from
human feedback.
And the fourth stage is
inference.
Now, let's look at the big picture.
What is that big picture?
We have 4 stages.
Pre -training, supervised fine
-tuning,
RLHF, and then we have the last one,
which is called as inference.
And here we have pre -training,
right?
This is where companies have to
spend millions of dollars.
Because we have to scrape all of our
internet data.
We have data from every source.
And we have to dump all of that data
inside this.
In that pre -training stage.
We have 100 million dollars,
right?
Most of the time, all of the money
goes into this step,
which is called pre -training.
And what is the second one?
Supervised fine -tuning.
This is not that costly.
What this does is,
we have a set of people.
They will write question answers.
Meaning, we have to answer this
question like this.
We have to answer this question like
this.
So, the model, ChatGPT,
will learn
how to answer correctly.
And then the third stage is RLHF.
Have you ever seen,
whenever you are asking ChatGPT,
you get 2 options.
Which one do you prefer?
Even that is human feedback.
What is happening there?
ChatGPT is providing an answer.
You are choosing which answer is
good,
you are providing a feedback to
ChatGPT.
Even that is counted as RLHF.
And after that,
once all of these 3 stages are done,
that is where the model training
will be completed.
And the last stage is inference.
We all use inference.
If you go to ChatGPT and type
some questions,
you are getting answers,
right?
That is what inference is.
Once the model is trained,
you are just going to ask the
questions
and it will answer you.
So, keep this diagram in your head.
And every time when I explain a
topic,
we are coming back to this diagram.
So, what should we do now?
Let's understand every stage
what happens even more clearly.
Now, let's start with our first
step,
which is called pre -training.
There are multiple sub -steps in pre
-training.
The first step is data collection.
Our first boy, the child,
he goes to the school
and there he is absorbing all of the
data.
Otherwise, our ChatGPT or Claude
cannot absorb all of the data,
right?
We need to collect the data
and we need to take that data and
give it to them.
So, where are we going to collect
the data?
And one of the common examples is
basically common crawl data.
What is common crawl data?
This is a free open source data set.
The data in our entire internet has
been collected.
Every website, every blog post,
every form,
we are going to scrape the entire
internet
and assume how much data will be
there in the internet?
It will be in petabytes,
guys.
Do you know what petabyte means?
1 petabyte is equal to 1000
terabytes.
That's a massive amount of data.
We need to store all this data,
right?
We will come to that point in the
later part.
And then we have something called as
GitHub.
Yes, in GitHub,
some lakhs, thousands,
crores of people
are pushing the code into the
GitHub,
JavaScript, Python, C,
C++, Rust, Go,
all these are written in different
languages.
So, we are going to collect all of
that data
and we will feed that into ChatGPT.
And that's why ChatGPT can write the
code in any language.
And then we have something
which is called as Wikipedia.
We are going to scrape the entire
Wikipedia,
even with the history as well in
Wikipedia.
And we have something called as
Books.
And there are billions of millions
of public books, guys.
We will scrape all of that data.
And we have something called as
academic papers,
reddit, forums, stack overflow.
I mean, there is no limit to how
much of data
that you can collect.
The more available we are,
the more data we can collect,
every single thing.
And how much of the data that we are
talking about,
do you have any idea?
Because, by collecting all this
data,
we are feeding it to ChatGPT or
Claude or Gemini, right?
So, there is one simple statistic.
So, when ChatGPT 3 came in the
beginning,
it has trained on 300 billion
tokens.
Do you remember our tokens video?
If you don't remember tokens,
please watch the video
and then come back to this video
now.
And ChatGPT 4,
we don't even know exact numbers
of how many tokens it has trained.
And LLaMA 3, which is a model from
Facebook,
it has been trained on 15 million
tokens.
So, on an average, a token is 3
fourths of a word, guys.
So, 15 trillion tokens is
approximately 11 trillion words.
Do you know how much information 11
trillion words is?
Let me give you an example.
Let's say, you are reading a book
24 hours a day
for 24 hours.
Similarly, you are reading for the
next 4 million years.
Then, you will consume 11 trillion
words.
Now, our model is,
how will it absorb all of this data?
We need something to process,
right?
So, now we are sending these 15
trillion tokens to a model.
To understand the model,
it needs to process.
And that is why we have the need for
GPUs.
Graphic processing units,
whether it is ChatGPT,
Claude or Grok,
they are being trained on hundreds
and thousands of GPUs.
And who provides these GPUs?
There is a company called NVIDIA.
And that is why the stock price of
NVIDIA is going up and up and up.
But there is one problem.
Do you know what that problem is?
Not all the data that you get from
the internet is clean.
Let's say I write a code and push it
in the database.
Maybe you could have written the
same code and pushed it.
There is a duplicate issue.
Maybe some people write the code and
it will not work,
but even then it will be on the
internet.
Why do we need a work chain code?
So the data is there,
but the data is not at all clean.
That is where the next step comes
into the picture,
which is called data cleaning.
There is a famous phrase in Telugu,
Jogi Jogi Ras Kute Budu Dey.
If our input data is dirty,
the output performance we get is
also dirty.
So we want the data to be as clean
as possible.
Otherwise, what kind of garbage are
we talking about?
You have scraped Wikipedia.
So on the same page,
it might appear in multiple
different websites.
Then you are duplicating the data,
right?
That is one kind of issue.
Maybe you are scraping the data.
I think it is a low quality code.
And if you put that low quality
code,
the model will also have a low
quality code.
That is not what we want.
And maybe hate speech.
There is a lot of hate on the
internet.
And if you give all this hate data
to the skill model,
it will try to reproduce that,
which we don't want at all.
And then maybe we have something
like personal information.
There is a lot of personal
information on the internet.
In my Instagram account,
Facebook account or YouTube.
We don't want to feed all of that
into the model, right?
And there are so many different
different steps,
different different techniques that
people use to clean the data.
So our end goal is,
we have a lot of data,
right?
That is all raw data,
which is not at all cleaned.
So we will put it in a funnel.
What do we do in that funnel?
We will do deduplication.
We will do language filtering.
We will do quality scoring.
And we will also do toxicity
filtering.
And we will also do PII removal.
That is personal information
removal.
And if you have 100 petabytes of
data,
after doing all this cleaning,
you might be ending up with 5 to 10
petabytes.
That is how the real world data is.
A lot of people don't talk about
this topic.
Because this is not the glamorous
step.
But this is where the intelligence
comes into picture.
If you send the trash, the trash
will come out.
If you send it clean, it will learn
it clean.
That is why companies like Google or
OpenAI,
they write a lot of papers on how
they clean the data as well.
Even in the companies,
we spend 60 to 80 % of our time on
data cleaning.
Because if the data is clean,
we get the output very clean without
much struggle.
And guys, here I am oversimplifying
a lot.
But actually, in real time,
they use a lot of techniques like
de -duplication, hashing techniques,
and near -de -duplication
techniques,
minimum hash, I mean custom
classifiers.
There are so many techniques that
OpenAI and Claude or Gemini will
use.
And we are not going to talk about
all of these in this video.
And the essence is,
we have dirty data.
We want to convert all of that dirty
data into clean data.
Such that we can feed all of that
clean data into the brain.
And after that,
the next step is what we call it as
a tokenizer.
I made a dedicated video about this
tokenizer.
If you haven't watched that video,
please go ahead and watch that
video.
Because we can't talk about the
tokenizer completely.
I will just give you a brief.
What is a tokenizer?
We have a text.
To convert that text into simple
words.
The cat sat on the mat.
It broken down into the cat sat on
the mat.
So we are breaking down an input
text into smaller chunks.
That is what we call it as a
tokenizer.
But in our previous video,
we learned about how to consume
tokens
when we are using charge,
or Claude or Gemini.
But here,
we are going to learn tokens on the
other side.
How to use tokens while training.
That is what it is.
So let's come to here.
Look here.
I can just put the cat sat on the
mat.
I have 6 tokens.
And I have token IDs as well.
And then the same thing,
if I put this word,
it is going to break it down into 6
tokens and 28 characters.
And if you put it in Telugu,
you get even more number of tokens
with the same small word.
Why?
I covered in detail in the tokens
video.
So the idea is,
first we collect the data.
We clean the data.
Then you break it down into tokens.
And you get the token IDs.
And by using the token IDs,
you convert them into embeddings.
So that is what it is.
And the charge bit,
usually they use something called
as byte pair encoding,
BPE.
At a high level,
it looks at the training data
and finds the most common pairs of
characters.
After that,
it will merge all of them into a
single token
and repeat this process
multiple thousands of times.
And after that,
it will create a vocabulary.
In our data set,
how many tokens we have,
and it is going to give the number
to each and every token.
That is what OpenAI usually does.
And we will not be covering all of
these
technical details in the same video
because if we cover BPE,
it will take an entire video
usually.
What did we do now?
By tokenization, you got the
numbers.
But these numbers are just IDs.
Hi and Hello
We got two numbers.
But the charge bit will not be able
to understand
Hi and Hello conveying the same
message.
That is where the next step comes
into the picture
which we will cover
a topic called embeddings.
Do you remember our tokens?
We have converted every token into
numbers
using ASCII values.
But that has a problem
there is no difference between Hi
and Hello.
So how are we going to solve that?
That is where embeddings come into
picture.
What are our steps?
We collected the data in the
beginning
then we cleaned the data
we put the cleaned data
into something called as tokenizer
we break it into chunks
and we got token IDs for every
chunk.
Now we will put these token IDs
into something called as embedding
layer.
What this embedding layer does is
it will convert
every single token ID
into a length of vector.
That length could be different from
different
different embedding techniques.
We will have dedicated video on
embeddings later on
because many of you have requested
this video. I will be working on
that
and I will upload the video on
embeddings
in detail. So don't worry on that
part.
Now what is the importance of this?
When I convert king and queen
into embeddings
they are very close
to each other
because they are very close to
semantical
meaning. And apple and banana
will be close to each other.
Dog and cat
But apple and dog
will not be close to each other.
So the high level information is
to convert these token IDs
into vectors
that is where embeddings will be
used
and these embeddings will be in such
a way that the semantical
meaning of all of these words are
retained.
So let me
quickly go into the Google Colab.
I am using an OpenAI API
and after that I am using
an embedding model called text-
embedding-3-small.
What am I doing here?
I am creating the embeddings for the
king
and I am creating embeddings
for the queen and I am creating
embeddings
for the apple. So after these
what is their length?
So right now ChatGPT provides an
embeddings
which are of length 1536
and after that
for these 3 embeddings
we are calculating distance
that is what we are printing here.
If I execute this
see
so the dimensions are 1536
but for king and queen
the distance is 0.5
and the similarity is very high
and for king and apple the
similarity is very less
that is what we are calculating here
and that is how
the embeddings are capturing
the semantic meaning of these words.
Okay, all this is good
but Mr. Balaji
you explained the data collection,
data cleaning, tokenization
and embeddings very well.
But how
does the model learn all of these
numbers?
That is the interesting stuff right?
Yes, that is where neural networks
comes into the picture
and I am going to explain neural
networks
in under 2 minutes guys,
no phd required.
What is neural networks?
Our human brain is there right?
Every communication
in our human brain is
depending on a component called
neurons. So taking
our human brain as inspiration
and replicating
them mathematically
is neural networks. So what are
neural networks?
Neural networks are a series of math
operations. Here we have
our input. What is this input?
Our text is converted into tokens
and embedding is done right?
That is what we are going to pass as
an input
and inside this
we have these which are called
hidden units.
And our data will
pass through all of these units
and here every hidden unit
we call it as a layer.
This is layer 1
layer 2, layer 3
and in real time we have
insane number of layers.
So what is the job of these layers?
Every layer will capture
some kind of information.
Let's say you have sent a text
maybe first layer will understand
its sarcasm, second layer
will understand its emotions
and third layer will understand
something funny
or grammar or punctuation.
So when the data passes
through all of these layers
these layers are learning
the importance and the
language of the data.
Where will all that learning be?
Those are what we call it as
weights.
These connections are there right?
These connections are what we call
it as learnings
and after all this is learned
when we ask a question
if we send this question to the
input
based on all of these learnings
we are going to get an output
which is called a prediction.
Very simple. I mean
it's not that simple but at least at
a high level
it's a simple topic right?
If you want to understand more
clearly
let's take water filter analogy
we have dirty water
when we take that dirty water and
put it in filters
every layer is doing some kind of
filtration right?
and at the end you get better water
or purified water
so similarly
we are sending our text
every layer is learning something
and at the end the model learned
every single thing
and in these neural networks
there is something called as
parameters
and parameters means
the learning weights
when these parameters change
the focus of the model is going to
change
that's why ChatGPT
works one way
and Claude works another way
because the parameters that it got
trained on
are very different from these models
and just to give you an example
ChatGPT 3 has 175 billion
parameters
billion parameters
and ChatGPT 4
I think the estimated is
1.8 trillion parameters
and ChatGPT 5.5
I don't even know how many trillion
parameters it has
and the next topic in the pre
-training
which is called
transformers
this is what made LLMs came true
ChatGPT, Gemini, Grok
in 2017
google released
a paper which is called
attention is all you need
this paper changed every
single thing
before transformers
we have something called as RNNs and
LSTMs
what they do is
they process the text in the left
to right sequential manner
and when each one of them processes
they tend to get lost
in their direction
so if the text is too large
then they will not able to remember
the initial text
so what this paper did
this paper will take all the text at
once
and there are two super powers for
this paper
one is positional encodings
let's say
the bank of the river
and I went to the bank
so the word bank is same in English
but semantically
the bank of the river is different
I went to the bank
and the bank is different
and I also need to remember
where this bank is
that is what we have something
called as positional encodings
with our text encodings
they introduce this positional
encodings
so the model
the brain will remember
which text is going where and how
this is very very important
same word different meaning
depending on the surrounding words
and position
so this is the first thing
and the second super power is
attention
so let's say I have sentence
the cat sat on the mat because it
was tired
here what is it
you know that it is basically a cat
because you have studied English
so you are a human being
but what is this it means
that is where the
attention comes into picture
for each token the model decides
which other tokens
matter the most
attention helps the connect distant
words
and capture the context
so let's say there is a big sentence
a big paragraph
so because of this attention
mechanism
the model will understand all of
that context
without losing their information
in this video we will not talk about
the technical details of attention
is all you need paper
that will only take separate
video all together
but at a high level attention is all
you need paper
we got all of these
models right now
which are possible to build like
ChatGPT
Claude or Gemini
so at a summary transformers means
positional encodings
plus attention plus feed forward
neural networks
so what did we do data collection
data cleaning and then
tokenization and then embeddings
and then neural networks
but in neural networks we use
transformers like neural networks
because to understand the position
and the attention as well
now we have data and architecture
but how does training happen
how does the model actually
learn where is the training
happening
and that is where we will talk about
the next step and the last step
the most important step the training
loop
now we have done all this right
now do you know what is the
objective of the model
by giving all of this data
it just need to predict the next
token that's it very simple
so let's say
model saw this
what is the capital of france
so model will take a guess
let's assume berlin
but berlin is a wrong answer
we know that because it is in our
data
so now it is a wrong answer
do you remember the parameters
in the neural networks topic
all of these weights
they will get tweaked a little bit
because the model predicted a wrong
answer and then
it will get tweaked until it gets
correct answer which is called paris
so whenever there is a mistake
happening
we evaluate that mistake
with the actual answer
and until that actual answer comes
we will change all of these weights
very interesting right
maybe let's take some more examples
i love eating dash
model will say food, that's good
change the knobs a little bit
the speed of light is approximately
what
and then speed of light is in
kilometers
i mean you get
every single question
after that every single token
the model will predict
based on whether the prediction is
correct
it will change the weights
based on these learning process
that's how the model learns the data
very simple
and now in our laptop
we have ram and cpu
we will process a lot of data
but here
we have terabytes, petabytes of data
where do you think all of these
processing will happen
neural networks will go
then we use
gpus
nvidia company will produce
these gpus and
apparently ChatGPT 4.5
to train that
nvidia company
they used 25000 gpus
and every single gpu
is costing a lot
for the continuous 6 months
approximately 80 million dollars
that is where the 100 million
dollar estimation came into the
picture
and just to remember
we learnt the model
but when you give a new question
which is what is the capital
of france
we have a base model
after learning all this
what will this model do
it will try to put the next word
then what will it say
what is the capital of germany
what is the capital of spain
it doesn't know how to answer
to your question
why
remember our first diagram
this model is a base model
which is our kid
it has consumed all of this
information
and understand the patterns
but
in our step 2 teacher came
but where is the teacher
and that is where we come into the
next step
which is stage 2
supervised fine tuning
now lets talk about supervised fine
tuning
so what did the base model do
when you ask a question
what is the capital of france
it doesn't know how to answer
that is why it says
what is the capital of germany
what is the capital of spain
the next word will go
and now we will
find that solution to it
by writing some examples
that is why
we are calling it
as a fine tuning
and why it is supervised
because actual humans
are writing these questions and
answers
so what is python
how to answer this
python is a high level programming
language
known for its readability and
simplicity
it is widely used in web development
and data science and AI
so humans will create these kind of
question and answers
and all these questions will be
fed to our base model
now it understands how to answer
in a proper way
for example one more example explain
the question
like a 10 year old
so we will
fine tune
the base model
so after doing all of
this supervised fine tuning
we will get a model
and that is what we call
instruction tuned model
so as summary
humans will write a lot of
conversations
we will feed
all those conversations to the base
model
so it understands
how to do, how to tell,
how to reply
and that is what we have
instruction following assistant
and then the next step
in our stages
which is RLHF
reinforcement learning
so what is reinforcement learning
let's say you asked a question in
charge
how do I make a bomb
one person gave a direct answer
that is not good right
you should not give that kind of
answers
so what will charge say
I cannot help with that
if you are in a dangerous situation
please contact
local authorities and there is
some people who put
these guardrails
they are putting feedback
is it correct to give
such an answer to such a question
that is what we are giving as a
feedback
if you have noticed
sometimes when you ask a question
charge jpt will give you two answers
even that is also
a human feedback actually
so these human preferences
are what we call it as a
reward model
and there is a small model that
would
predict what a human would like
this is what makes charge jpt
good for you
the personalized assistant for you
because it keeps on learning
from your feedback
and after all this
the one that you got
is basically the charge jpt
that you are using as a fully
trained
and ready to be deployed to the
world
and how is that deployment happening
and the question is being controlled
that is what we have
as an inference
that is the last stage
so after all this process is done
now we have
this model charge jpt 4
or mini or 5.5
then we have the question
what is python
by using the API
that is what inference is
that is what the stage 4
is
so if you see
it is going to predict token by
token
token by token
it is giving you the answer
and it is the same thing
that you are going to look at
inside the charge jpt,
Claude, Gemini
all of these are the inferences
already 100 million models
are trained
now we are going to use these models
by just inferencing to those models
now let us connect all of these
LLM behaviors
sometimes the charge jpt does
mistakes
because those are what we call
hallucinations
because the model is predicting
the likely tokens
it is not understanding what comes
next
that is why hallucinations happen
and knowledge cut off date
what is knowledge cut off date
we gathered the data in the
beginning
so to gather that data
and then to train it
there is a space of 6 months
that means our data collection
stopped before 6 months
so how does it know the latest data
it does not know right
that is why all of these models will
have the knowledge cut off
and then the refusals
few questions key
it will not answer
because there is human feedback
that is in the back end
which says don't answer to these
kind of questions
you can also think about these as
guardrails as well
and then we have
different personalities
this also depends on your feedback
and then the important stuff
cost per token
now if you spend 100 million dollars
and train them
they are going to get the value back
so how does that value come
they are charging you
for every single token
for every token
you will pay some amount of money
so it will have one price per charge
and depending on the model
the price will also change
input tokens will change,
output tokens will change
a lot of stuff
and then slower response and longer
complex prompts
why
when you are inferencing
if you put more text
you have to process it and reply to
it
that is why it is taking
longer responses
and then why it is better at English
why not it is better at Telugu
because usually
you have a lot of data in English
rather than Telugu
and that is why the model is little
bit biased
towards English
and before we close this
I wanted to say
this is what
the mental model of an LLM is
so this is where we will understand
what is LLM
what is training, what is knowledge
cut off
what is probability generation
why some prompts give different
outputs
so we understood
what is LLM
after that we will also understand
RAG, prompt engineering
tools, MCPs
and a lot of different interesting
topics
that we are going to learn in the
upcoming videos
if you like the video
please subscribe
and also comment something
in the comment box
so that I know that you guys are
enjoying these videos
and it gives me motivation to make
even more videos
and if you think someone else might
also need
this video, please share it with
them
thank you and signing off